While
Speaker 1: you've been watching the Discovery Channel and their Shark Week programming, I
want to talk
Speaker 1: about another form of predatory shark, the payday loan shark. Here we have our payday loan shark and here we have the American family that's in choppy financial waters trying to raise money to perhaps to pay their rent or some medical expenses or a car repair. And while they're in the choppy waters, the loan shark is offering a life raft, a very appealing life raft.
Speaker 1: and saying, "This will help you meet those basic expenses." Well, the way this works is the family then signs up for that initial loan, they take it out to pay those basic expenses, and that looks pretty good, but it's only a two-week loan. And also, it has very high interest rates, perhaps 300 to 500% annual interest rates. This type of interest rate is absolutely destructive to a family.
Speaker 1: What it means is that in one year a $1,000 loan becomes a $5,000 loan, in two years a $25,000 loan. And families are trapped in these loans because in two weeks when the loan is due, they most of the time can't repay. Eighty percent of families, four out of five families, cannot repay. So they have to roll over the loan. And so they take it out, it's probably a little bit larger loan, and now that puts them further into this vortex of debt.
Speaker 1: And as it goes week after week after week, they sink deeper and deeper and deeper. And at the bottom of this vortex, families end up in default and bankruptcy. This is enormously damaging to American families and to the children of those families. And we need to stop this. In fact, our military leaders have said this is so destructive to our military families, make these loans illegal. And we have.
But
Speaker 1: let's do the same thing for all American families. What's destructive to our military families is destructive to every family. And that's why we need to do two things. We need to move to cap the interest rates on these loans to very low levels, as so many states have done. And second of all, we need to support the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau as it cracks down on these payday lenders. Let's stop the payday loan sharks from drowning our families in this vortex of debt.
For more information, visit www.fema.org.